A Guide to the Stettinius Family Genealogical Research Files, 1801-2004
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Stettinius Family Genealogical Research Files, 1801-2004
Library of Virginia
41217
3.60 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Joseph Stettinius, March 2004.
Biographical Information
Edward Reilly Stettinius was born in 1865 and married Judith Carrington. He died in 1925. His son Edward Reilly Stettinius, Jr. was born 22 October 1900 in Chicago, Illinois and was married to Virginia Gordon Wallace. He served as Secretary of State under President Roosevelt from the end of 1944 until the early summer of 1945. He died on 31 October 1949. His son was Joseph Stettinius.
Scope and Content
Genealogical research files, 1801-2004 (bulk 1938-2004), of the Stettinius family and related family lines principally compiled by Joseph Stettinius. There are also files compiled by Edward Stettinius, Jr. and his father Edward Stettinius. These files generally remain in the order kept by Joseph Stettinius. This collection also contains electronic research files compiled by Joseph Stettinius in electronic format using Family Tree Maker software. Non-genealogical information in this collection consists of the personal correspondence, 1913-1923, of Edward Stettinius exchanged with Carrington family members. Also includes a German fraktur of a baptismal certificate of Jonathon Mosttram, printed by E. Stettinius.
Arrangement
Organized into the following four series: I. Genealogical research files; II. Electronic genealogical research files; III. Edward Stettinius personal correspondence; IV. German Fraktur.
Contents List
- Genealogical Research Files, 1865, 1913-2004 (Boxes 1-8)
  Consists of research files concerning specific individuals and families and correspondence exchanged with individuals concerning specific families. Contains genealogical notes concerning family lines abstracted and/or copied from genealogical internet websites, census records, family group sheets, pedigree charts, extracts from published sources, newspaper clippings, photographs, genealogical charts and court records. Correspondence written to research institutions, family members, and genealogical researchers concerning family lines also appears in this collection and includes research files along with the letters. This material remains filed under the respective correspondent's name. Notable family surnames researched include Beeler, Buck, Carrington, Cooke, Craig, Gamage, Handy, Harriott, Harte, Havemeyer, Holmead, Hyatt, Kneller, MacLannen, Mercer, Shepherd, Wallace and Wharton.
  Alphabetically and then chronologically within each folder.
  - Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Folk Art Collection, correspondence with, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Barco, Andi, correspondence with, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barnitz, Mary, correspondence with, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Beeler family, research files, 1963-1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Beeler-Beller family, family group charts, ca. 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bermuda Archives, correspondence with, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bermuth, Mrs. Charles M. Von, correspondence with, 1961-1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bethune-Row family, research files, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bornkraber, Kathe, correspondence with, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bridge House Art Gallery (Bermuda), correspondence with, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Briscoe, Ruth, correspondence with, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Brubaker, Anita, correspondence with, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bryan, Stewart, correspondence with, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Buck, Ginger, correspondence with, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Buck-Shepherd family, research files, 1999-2003 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bureau of Vital Statistics, Baltimore, Maryland, correspondence with, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - California Historical Society, correspondence with, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - California State Library, correspondence with, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Campbell, Tom, correspondence with, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Cana, Mary Ann, copy of will of, written 23 December 1835 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Carrington family, research files, 1947-1977 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Carrington family, research files, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Carrington family, research files, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Cavalry Cemetery and Mausoleum, correspondence with, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Clerk of Chicago, Illinois, correspondence with, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Colorado Historical Society, correspondence with, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Conness, Rosalie, correspondence with, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Cooke family, research files, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Cooke, Thomas, correspondence with, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Cooke-Herzog-Esten family, research files, 1972-1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Craig family, research files, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Crandall, John H., correspondence with, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Davis, Andrew J., correspondence with, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Endredi-Stettinius coat of arms, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Engle, Elizabeth, correspondence with, 1998-2003 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Episcopal Diocese, Washington, D. C., correspondence with, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Filson Club Historical Society, correspondence with, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - First and Franklin Street Presbyterian Church, correspondence with, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Fletcher, Mildred, correspondence with, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Folkes, Minetree, Jr., correspondence with, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Freeman, Harold C., correspondence with, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Frick Art Reference Library, correspondence with, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Gamage family, research files, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Gatti, Arnold and Carol, correspondence with, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General Services Administration, correspondence with, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - George Washington University, correspondence with, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Goodfellow, Helen C., correspondence with, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Handy family, genealogical chart, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Handy family, research files, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The Handy Family, by W. Thomas Hall, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Harriott, Josephine T., Mrs. E. R. Stettinius' correspondence concerning estate of, 1937-1945 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Harriott, Josephine T., general correspondence and files concerning estate of, February-April 1946 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Harriott, Josephine T., general correspondence and files concerning estate of, 1864, 1940-January 1946 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Harrison, Hager Stettinius, correspondence with, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Harte, Edward H., correspondence with, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Harte family, research files, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Hatcher family, research files, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Havemeyer family, genealogical chart, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Havemeyer family, "Notes Relating to Havemeyer Family," compiled by an unknown author, ca. 1944 (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
  - Havemeyer family, "Notes Relating to Havemeyer Family," compiled by an unknown author (copy 2), ca. 1944 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Havemeyer family, photographs, ca. 1865-1880 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Henius, Elizabeth Koones, correspondence with, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Heyt, Isabel B., correspondence with, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Hildrup family, research files, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Hildrup, Keith and Kerry C., correspondence with, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Holliday, Curtis, correspondence with, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Holmead family, research files, 1962, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Holmead family, research files, 2001, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Holy Cross Cemetery, correspondence with, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Huntington, Anna H., correspondence with, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Huntington Library, correspondence with, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Hyatt family, research files (1 of 2), 2000, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Hyatt family, research files, (2 of 2), 2004 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Indiana State Library, correspondence with, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "James Nourse and His Descendants," by Maria Lyle (partial copy), 1897 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Kelsch, Gerald T., correspondence with, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Kentucky Historical Society, correspondence with, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - King, George Harrison Sanford, correspondence with, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Kluge, Ralph W., correspondence with, 1964-1965, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Kneller-McClennan family, research files, 1993 and n.d. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Lawson, Jaime, correspondence with, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Lewis, John Latane, III, correspondence with, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Library of Virginia, correspondence with, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Longworth family, research files, 2000, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Lowe, J. Mark, correspondence with, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Lowe, J. Mark, correspondence with, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - MacDonald, Peg, correspondence with, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - McLaughlin, Catherine Koones, correspondence with, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Marsh family, research files, 1935, 1961-1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Maryland Historical Society, research files, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Maxwell family, research files, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Mercer, Hugh, correspondence with, 1966-1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Mercer, Hugh, publications concerning, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - Mercer, Hugh, research files concerning, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Minnesota Historical Society, correspondence with, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Missouri Historical Society, correspondence with, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous families, research files, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous families, pedigree charts, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Morrison family, research files, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Nidiffer Collection, research files from, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Nourse family, research files, 2002, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Old correspondence, transcripted by Joseph Stettinius(?), originally written 1824-1835 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Padgett, Charles, correspondence with, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Patton family, research files, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Patton, Jay, correspondence with, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Pennsylvania Historical Society, correspondence with, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Peoria Historical Society, correspondence with, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Peter, Phillips Smith, correspondence with, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Petersburg, City of, correspondence with, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Petersburg Public Library, correspondence with, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Petre, Cathy, correspondence with, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Petre family, research files, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Phillips family, research files, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Pratt, Beverly C., correspondence with, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Pre-American history (German Stettinius family), correspondence with, 1933-1973 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Prince George County (Md.) Historical Society, correspondence with, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Rankin, John, correspondence with, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Read, Clement, research files concerning, 2002-2003 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Ridge, Linda, correspondence with, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Rogers family, publications concerning, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Saffold, Lenora Reach, correspondence with, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - St. George's Episcopal Church, correspondence with, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - St. George's Foundation, calendars, 2001-2002 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - St. George's Town Heritage: Bringing History to Life, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - St. Joseph's College, correspondence with, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - St. Louis Catholic Cemetery, correspondence with, 2000, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - St. Louis Genealogical Society, correspondence with, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - St. Louis Department of Health, correspondence with, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - St. Matthew's Lutheran Church, correspondence with, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - St. Peter's Cemetery, correspondence with, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Second Presbyterian Church, correspondence with, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Smith, Phillips, correspondence with, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Snell, George B., correspondence with, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Stamm, Patricia, correspondence with, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Standard, Raymond, correspondence with, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Stettinius Baltimore family, correspondence with, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Stettinius, Crystal, correspondence with, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Stettinius, Derrick J., copies of estate records of, 1894-1895 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Stettinius, Edward R., Jr., correspondence with or information concerning, 1934-1963 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Stettinius, Edward R., III, correspondence with, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Stettinius European family, correspondence with, 1989-1999 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Stettinius family, census records, 1830-1840 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Stettinius family, miscellaneous correspondence concerning, 1965-2002 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Stettinius family, miscellaneous correspondence with, 1972-2004 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Stettinius family, photographs, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Stettinius family, research files, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Stettinius family, research files, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Stettinius family, research files, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Stettinius family, research files, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Stettinius family, research files, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Stettinius family, research files, 2004 and n.d. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Stettinius, George W., research files concerning, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Stettinius, Isabel, copy of will of, 1891 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Stettinius, John G., correspondence with, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Stettinius, John W. D., correspondence with, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Stettinius, Josef Frederick family, research files concerning, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Stettinius, Melvin, correspondence with, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Stettinius, Samuel E., "The Descendants of Samuel Enredi Stettinius," by an unknown compiler, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Stettinius, Samuel E., "The Descendants of Samuel Enredi Stettinius," by an unknown compiler (copy 2), 1962 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Stettinius, Ted, correspondence with, 1999-2003 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Stettinius, Virginia, legal briefs and appendices in the Second Circuit Court of Appeals, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Stettinius, Virginia, correspondence with her father William J. Wallace, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Stettinius, William, copy of research notes of, 1883 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Sunday Star (Washington, D. C. newspaper), correspondence with and articles concerning Stettinius family, 1940-1945 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Taylor, David F., correspondence with, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Taylor, Maurice S., correspondence with, 1944, 1961-1962 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Thornton family, research files, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Thornton, Heber L., correspondence with or concerning family of, 1961-1962, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Tripp, Elizabeth S., correspondence with, 1960-1972 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Tucker family, pedigree charts, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Turner, Elizabeth C., correspondence with, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Tuttle, Sue, correspondence with, 1999-2001 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - University of California at Berkeley, correspondence with, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - University of Virginia, correspondence with, 1941-1966 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Vanneck, John, correspondence with, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Vermont Historical Society, correspondence with, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Wallace family, correspondence with, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Wallace family, research files, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Wallace, William J., correspondence with, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Walsh, Diane, correspondence with, 2000-2001 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Wann family, research files, 1970 and n.d. (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Wharton family, research files, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Wight, Elizabeth, correspondence with, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Wilson, Elizabeth S., correspondence with, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Wilson, Perkins, correspondence with, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Winston family, research files, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Wolfe, Nell T., correspondence with, 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Woodford, Katharine D., correspondence with, 1961-1969 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Woodford, Walter E., correspondence with, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - York County Historical Society, correspondence with, 1938-1961 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - York County Historical Society, Stettinius family art portraits by S. E. Stettinius, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Electronic Genealogical Research Files, Two compact disks and one zip disk. (Box 7, Folder 26a)
  Research files compiled by Joseph Stettinius in computer format on Family Tree Maker software and containing biographical and family information concerning the Stettinius and related families.
- Edward Stettinius Personal Correspondence, 1913-1923 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  Letters and postcards sent principally from Emma Carrington in Richmond, Virginia, but also from other family members to Edward Stettinius, Jr. Principally concerns family matters and family health and illnesses, but there is also one letter from Philip Alexander Bruce to Edward Stettinius' mother Judith Carrington Stettinius concerning a possible article about the James River Canal. Also includes an undated namecard for Edward R. Stettinius, Jr.
  Arranged chronologically within the folder.
- German Fraktur (Box 8, Folder 8)
  Baptismal certificate of Jonathon Mosttram, born to August Bernard and Eva Mosttram, on 18 December 1801 and baptized on 30 January 1802 in York County, Pennsylvania. The fraktur was printed by W. Lepper and E. Stettinius. Also includes a translation.